Today's דף daf is ל"ד, lamed dalet, 34. We start a little
bit behind, we're on ל"ג עמוד ב' lamed gimmel amud bet by
the two dots, ואין ממעטין ביום טוב, ve'ein mematin beyom tov, still
talking about the הדס hadas and removing the berries, and the ongoing
question has been whether there's this issue called דיחוי במצוות, dichuy bi-mitzvot,
whether a מצוה mitzvah object, if it was initially unusable when it
became originally defined as the מצוה mitzvah object, whether that status of
being unusable or rejected remains even after it becomes fit again. So
until now, we've been avoiding coming to any particular conclusion about that,
about whether there is דיחוי dichuy or not דיחוי, dichuy, but now
we turn to the last clause in the משנה, mishnah, which is
you cannot remove the berries on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So let's
take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, about fifteen lines down in
the middle of ל"ג עמוד ב'. lamed gimmel amud bet. העבר ולקטן,
ha'avar ve-liktan,
so if you transgressed and you actually did pick some berries on
יום טוב Yom Tov off of this הדס, hadas, מאי, mai, so
what would be the status? כשר. kasher. It sounds like it would
be כשר, kasher, just sounds like you're not allowed to, but that
the actual הדס hadas would then become כשר kasher as a result.
So דאשחר אמש, de-ashchar emosh, when did it become black? Because as
we said yesterday, it's only compared, it's only a problem when the
berries are actually black. אילימא דאשחר מאתמול, eilima de-ashchar me'etmol, if they've
been black already and the הדס hadas had been invalid before יום
טוב Yom Tov began, so דיחוי מעיקרא הוא, dichuy mei'ikara hu, so
then at least when יום טוב Yom Tov began, it was already
pushed away, it was unusable when יום טוב Yom Tov began.
And yesterday we tried to claim that it wasn't clear whether that
would be a problem. Here you see that it would not be
a problem because even if it was pushed away, not usable when
יום טוב Yom Tov began, you could make it usable on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. I mean, you're not allowed to, but it would
become usable. תפשוט מינה, tifshot mineh,
so you should at least be able to infer from that, דיחוי
מעיקרא דלא הוי דיחוי, dichuy mei'ikara delo havei dichuy, that if it
was initially unusable, that's not considered that it doesn't necessarily have to
remain that way. אלא לאו, ela lav, so okay, as an alternative,
we'll try to argue the second possibility, דאשחר ביום טוב, de-ashchar beyom
tov,
maybe no, when יום טוב Yom Tov began they were fine, they
just became black over יום טוב, Yom Tov, and then you fixed
it again. But when יום טוב Yom Tov began, it was okay.
If that's true, נראה ונדחה הוא, nireh ve-nidcheh hu,
that's a case where it was originally fit when יום טוב Yom
Tov began and then it got pushed away. And then your conclusion
would be שמע מינה, shema mina, then you could infer from that
נראה ונדחה חוזר ונראה, nireh ve-nidcheh chozer ve-nireh, that if something was
fit and pushed away, it can become fit again. Now of those
two, it's actually it's easier to validate the case when it was
never fit. Right? If something was actually in the category and rejected,
right, then it's harder to go ahead and to make it more
acceptable because it was like actively pushed away after it already was
fully in that category. If something was like never fit even when
it became a מצוה mitzvah object, it's more
like come back and see us when you're ready. So then when
it becomes fit, maybe that's different. But so if you had a
choice between the two, it's easier to say it's כשר, kasher, the
case of דיחוי מעיקרא dichuy mei'ikara than נראה ונדחה. nireh ve-nidcheh.
And the גמרא Gemara says that one of them has to be
okay. Because if you picked the berries on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
when יום טוב Yom Tov begins, it's in the category of the
מצוה. mitzvah. So either it was never fit and you made it
fit, or it was fit, unfit, and you made it fit again.
One of those at least is going to be כשר. kasher. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
so let's go back to the first possibility, דאשחר מעיקרא. de-ashchar mei'ikara.
Let's at least concede the less, the more obvious case. It was
black when יום טוב Yom Tov began. דיחוי מעיקרא דלא הוי דיחוי
תפשוט מינה, dichuy mei'ikara delo havei dichuy tifshot mineh,
I'll concede that you can infer from this that something initially pushed
away does not have to remain that way. It was black, it
was unusable when יום טוב Yom Tov began. It was דיחוי מעיקרא
dichuy mei'ikara but then you picked the berries, you made it acceptable.
That you can infer from the משנה. mishnah. אבל נראה ונדחה חוזר
ונראה לא תפשוט, aval nireh ve-nidcheh chozer ve-nireh lo tifshot,
you cannot go so far to infer that fit and then pushed
away will become fit again because that's not necessarily the case. The
case was not necessarily that it was fit when יום טוב Yom
Tov began, it might have been the case it was unfit. But
minimally, you're right. Since it says don't pick the berries, the implication
being that if you picked the berries it's okay, you're right minimally
you could prove that if something was unfit when it began to
be a מצוה, mitzvah, when יום טוב Yom Tov began, that you
can go ahead and make it fit. At least you can prove
the case of נראה ונדחה. nireh ve-nidcheh. Now, by the way, you
could make even a stronger claim. You could say there's no such
concept of דיחוי במצוות. dichuy bi-mitzvot. Right? That was the question we
were asking yesterday. Right? Because then, okay, there's no concept of דיחוי,
dichuy, of course you can make it okay, the concept isn't relevant.
Here what the גמרא Gemara is saying is even if I were
to concede that there is a concept of דיחוי במצוות, dichuy bi-mitzvot,
at least we see from this case that the case of נדחה
מעיקרא nidcheh mei'ikara is not a problem. Right? If it started off
being pushed away, then you can go ahead and fix it. It
might be דיחוי dichuy is נישט nisht at all,
right? But... So at least דיחוי מעיקרא dichui mei-ikara is not a
problem. Yes.
So why does the גמרא Gemara not entertain the possibility of הותרה?
hutra? In other words, if this whole thing is being compared to
קדשים, kodshim, right? So like there's a concept of דיחוי dichui by
קדשים, kodshim, right? This applies to מצווה. mitzvah. What about the issue
of... what's that issue by קדשים? kodshim? Is it דיחוי dichui or
הותרה? hutra? One of those two?
Oh, that's a different concept of דיחוי. dichui. That's about...
no, no, no. So you're right, I mean it's the same word,
but that's when there's an issue that there's something that overrides that
lets you bring it like you're... you're overriding it and allowing you
to bring it on שבת Shabbat or overriding it and allowing you
to bring it בטומאה. be-tumah. So do you say that it's הותרה
hutra or דחויה? duchuya? So is the prohibition pushed away or is
the prohibition completely allowed, completely released? Here it's whether the מצווה mitzvah
object is pushed away, so it's a different concept. Here it's more
of a stigma, the idea of דיחוי. dichui. Alright, okay, so that's
the conclusion. The conclusion is, is that minimally there's not a problem
of דיחוי מעיקרא, dichui mei-ikara, and if you pick the berries on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, you'll make it okay. Okay, it might be
there's no problem of דיחוי dichui at all, but minimally there's not
that problem. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. אין
ממעטין ביום טוב. Ein mematin be-Yom Tov. Now we turn to the
issue about why that you can't pick the berries on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. משום רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אמרו ממעטין. Mishum Rabbi Elazar
berabi Shimon amru mematin. But רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabi
Shimon says you are allowed to pick the berries. So the גמרא
Gemara said, how could you do that? והא קמתקן מנא ביום טוב?
Ve-ha ka-metaken mana be-Yom Tov? You're fixing something on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, you're making this הדס hadas into a usable הדס. hadas. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, כגון שלקטן לאכילה. kegon she-liktan le-achilah. You're
not trying to fix הדס, hadas, you're picking the berries because you
like the berries, you're eating them. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, ורבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון סבר לה כאבוה, Ve-Rabbi Elazar berabi
Shimon savar lah ke-avuhu, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon
holds like his
father, דאמר דבר שאינו מתכוון מותר, de-amar davar she-eino mitkaven mutar, because
his father, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, holds that you can do something
on שבת Shabbat or יום טוב Yom Tov if you're not intending
for the consequences. You're trying to just eat the berries, you're not
trying to fix it. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. והא
אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו, Ve-ha Abaye ve-Rava de-amri tarveihu, אביי ורבא Abaye
ve-Rava both say מודה רבי שמעון בפסיק רישא ולא ימות, modeh Rabbi
Shimon bi-psik reisha ve-lo yamut, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees if you
cut off its head won't it die? And it's so meaning you
can say the classic example of אינו מתכוון eino mitkaven is I
can drag a bench across the yard to get it from one
end of the yard to the other. Oh, maybe it'll make a
furrow. Alright, I'm not trying to make a furrow. And you know
what? A furrow won't even necessarily be made, depends how soft the
ground is, depends how hard I'm dragging. So therefore we could say
that if a furrow is made, it's an unintended consequence and it's
not like I did it. But they say let's say the ground
is so soft and the bench is so heavy that there's no
question you're going to make a furrow. So you can't say, well,
I wasn't intending to make a furrow, I was only intending to
drag the bench across. No, since it was a necessary consequence, it's
like you intended it. They said let's say you were to chop
off the head of a chicken and you were saying, I just
want to play with the head, I'm not interested in a dead
chicken, that was an unintended consequence. You can't say unintended if it'll
necessarily happen. So therefore you cannot use אינו מתכוון eino mitkaven in
a case called a פסיק רישא, psik reisha, a cutoff the head,
where it's a necessary consequence. So they say if you pluck off
the berries, making it a usable הדס hadas is a necessary consequence.
It's not maybe it will, maybe it won't. So the fact that
you weren't intending it does not get you off the hook, does
not make it like it don't attribute this action to me.
By the way, it's not a necessary consequence. Why? Because it could
be something else wrong with the leaves.
Okay, but in a case where it is usable, then it's a
necessary consequence. And that's got to be the case because
otherwise you'd assume that if you did it, it would make a
כשר הדס. kasher hadas. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay,
so the
גמרא Gemara says דאית ליה הושענא אחריתי. de-it leih hoshanah achriti. You
have another הדס. hadas. Now why does that matter? So here you
have a fascinating debate of רש"י ותוספות. Rashi ve-Tosafot.
רש"י Rashi says, and רש"י Rashi is like a very simple answer,
רש"י Rashi says look, when you look at a הדס hadas without
berries, what do you look at it as? Do you say like,
ah, now I've got a הדס hadas to use for my לולב?
lulav? Now I have a fixed הדס. hadas. Let's say you already
had, let me give you a scenario, let's say you already had
your לולב lulav with the הדס hadas and the ערבה aravah all
bound up and all ready to go, and then you were plucking
berries from another הדס. hadas. Would you say that you fixed the
הדס? hadas? No, in that type of a context you don't look
at this הדס hadas as now a fixed הדס. hadas. It was
just a like a you know it was it was just a
branch that had berries on it. It was like you had a
it was like you had a cluster of grapes that you were
picking grapes off of the cluster. In the context where you have
another הדס, hadas, this doesn't transform from being something like from being
identified as an unusable
הדס hadas to
It's not like the objective reality now makes it a different object.
It was only a different object when it was needed to serve
in that type of a capacity. תוספות Tosfot says another explanation. תוספות
Tosfot says that actually, and this becomes very important, it's a principle
called פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה, Psik Reisha Delo Nicha Lei, which
is not explicit in the גמרא, Gemara, but it's very much developed
by תוספות Tosfot and other ראשונים. Rishonim. Yes, it's a necessary consequence,
but it's not a consequence I'm interested in. And since it's not
a consequence you're interested in, it doesn't really be considered to be
something that is attributable to you. So if I like I wanted
the furrow in the ground, okay, meaning not like I was trying
to make it, but it would be nice for me to have
a furrow in the ground, then you say, ah, it was a
necessary consequence and it's something you're happy with. You know what it's
like? You intended it. But if basically you're not interested in the
furrow in the ground and it's not an intended consequence even if
it's necessary, then it can't be like it's sort of like you
wanted it. No, I didn't want it, you know? So even if
it was necessary, if I wasn't interested in it, don't make it
my issue. So that's what תוספות Tosfot says the case is here.
If you're not interested in it because anyway you've got another הדס,
Hadas, even though you did fix the הדס, Hadas, we're not disagreeing
with that conclusion, it is like you fixed it, but it's not
like something that was connected to you and therefore it can't be
pinned on you. Another way תוספות Tosfot goes it is, he even
goes so far to call it like a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה.
Melacha She'eina Tzricha Legufa. Like yes, you wanted to do it, but
not for the normal reason and therefore you can't be held, it
can't be tagged on you. Anyway, that's what תוספות Tosfot says. רש״י's
Rashi explanation seems at least here to be a lot more simpler.
In this context where you don't need a הדס, Hadas, it's not
considered like you fixed it. By the way, according to a number
of ראשונים, Rishonim, we're only dealing with a rabbinic problem to begin
with. Right? The idea that it's considered like, well, not, right, the
idea that it's fixing, like making something, you know, if you really
are making a vessel, you give the final hammer blow, you shape
it, then you make something. That's like an ענין Inyan of מכה
בפטיש Maka B'Patish or בונה. Boneh. Here, you know, just because now
it has the kosher qualities that you could use it in your
לולב, Lulav, according to some ראשונים, Rishonim, the רמב״ם, Rambam, it says
even if you did it intentionally, it's not a biblical מלאכה Melacha
anyway. So in that context, recognizing that it's a pretty amorphous idea
fixing it to begin with and you have another one anyway, so
you don't really, so in that context it's not really considered like
you did anything of substance. So that's what רש״י Rashi says. If
you have another one, you didn't really do anything. Or תוספות: Tosfot:
No, you did it, but since you weren't interested in it, it's
not really your problem, it's not really your act. That's how they
handle it. Yes.
Are you saying did I understand correctly that the distinction of פסיק
רישא דלא ניחא ליה Psik Reisha Delo Nicha Lei is introduced by
תוספות, Tosfot, not in the גמרא Gemara anywhere?
Right, the גמרא Gemara has this case and another case like it,
where a number of ראשונים Rishonim say, oh, this is an idea
called פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה Psik Reisha Delo Nicha Lei and
that's an exclusion. But a number of, it's possible to read the
cases in the גמרא Gemara to be very local reasons and not
a generic idea. For תוספות, Tosfot, which becomes a very dominant הלכה
Halacha category on שבת, Shabbat, that פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה Psik
Reisha Delo Nicha Lei is not so clear in the גמרא. Gemara.
Just so you know, yes.
So which of these concepts do you apply about the idea of
dragging the bench through the ground then? If you weren't at all
interested, do you, you're not responsible?
So according to תוספות, Tosfot, if you're not interested in the result,
you don't care about the end result, that's פסיק רישא דלא ניחא
ליה, Psik Reisha Delo Nicha Lei, which means that it would only
be like a rabbinic issue but you certainly would not be liable
and sometimes we might even say that it would be allowed. That's
what תוספות Tosfot says. רש״י Rashi never says that and other ראשונים,
Rishonim, again, that's how we פסקן Pasken like תוספות. Tosfot. But רש״י
Rashi and other ראשונים Rishonim don't agree and they say that no,
this case is special. This case, as opposed to the bench case,
you actually did make a furrow, you actually did do something whether
you're interested in it or not. Here, in this context, you didn't
do anything significant. So that's how רש״י Rashi reads it.
If you have another one, you didn't really do
anything.
I just looked up, myrtle berries actually are edible. I never seen.
There you go. Okay. It sounds like one of those Dr. Seuss,
which is the Dr. Seuss where they're always eating those berries off
of that was like, anyway.
Wait, so if you're, if
you're completely indifferent, that's considered לא ניחא ליה? Lo Nicha Lei?
Yeah. לא, the ראשונים Rishonim, don't distinguish between לא ניחא ליה Lo
Nicha Lei and לא איכפת ליה. Lo Ichpat Lei. Okay. לא ניחא
Lo Nicha is you don't want it, לא איכפת Lo Ichpat is
you don't care for it, they basically don't distinguish. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, so we taught.
הותר אגדו ביום טוב אוגדו כאגודה של ירק. Hutar Agdo B'Yom Tov
Ogdo K'Aguda Shel Yerek.
If the bunch, if the knot undoes, gets undone on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, you re-knot it like you make a vegetable bunch, which
is like you just wrap it around and you tuck it in.
So you don't even like knot it at all because you can't
make a knot on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the גמרא Gemara
says המני? Ha Mani? So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואמאי?
V'Amai? Why, why should you limit yourself to that? לענבי מענב, Le'anvei
Meanav, make it like a עניבה, Aniva, make a, okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says המני רבי יהודה היא דאמר עניבה קשירה מעליא היא.
Ha Mani Rabbi Yehuda Hi De'amar Aniva Keshira Ma'alya Hi. No, it's
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that a עניבה
Aniva is a real knot on שבת Shabbat and on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. He says it in another context and therefore it doesn't
make it any good, whether you're going to make a double knot
or a עניבה, Aniva, either way you
can't. you should have to then what good does it do to
make a like a like a little tucked-in type of a wrap?
According to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you're not יוצא yotzei unless you
really make a real knot. So according to it can't be רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. He wouldn't let you make any... for him it
wouldn't be good to do anything other than a real knot and
obviously you couldn't do that on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, האי תנא סבר לה כוותיה בחדא ופליג עליה
בחדא. Hai tanna savar lah kavateih be-chada u-palig leih be-chada. This תנא
tanna holds like him in one regard that he doesn't like bow
knots on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but he disagrees in another regard
and he actually feels that you're יוצא yotzei a לולב lulav without
doing a full knot.
He doesn't hold like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you really need a
knot, going back to the debate לולב צריך אגד, lulav tzarich eged,
so you can be יוצא yotzei this לולב lulav even if the
knot got undone. But even if you want to knot it and
לכתחילה lechatchila you should knot it on יום טוב, Yom Tov, don't
make a bow knot, that according to him would be a problem.
Now רש״י Rashi has a very important רש״י Rashi here according to
this. If you take a look at רש״י, Rashi, Rashi's lines towards
the word עלי, alei, three lines before the משנה Mishna in the
רש״י, Rashi, he says the following. בלולב דאין צריך אגד. be-lulav de-ein
tzarich eged. He says a לולב lulav doesn't need the knot so
he'll let you do a tucking in because you don't need to
really because בדיעבד bedieved you're יוצא yotzei even without a knot. שמעינן
מהכא Sheminan me-hacha says רש״י, Rashi, we can hear from here, דבעינן
בלולב קשר גמור, de-be'inan be-lulav kesher gamur, שיקשור שני ראשי האגד. she-yikshor
shenei rashei ha-eged.
So meaning according to we see, right, it says that according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda just tucking in would not be enough. According
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that לולב צריך אגד, lulav tzarich eged,
you'd have to make a real knot and you couldn't do it
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, so you're stuck, right? That's the גמרא's
Gemara conclusion. That according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you can't make
a real knot on יום טוב, Yom Tov, number one, and number
two therefore there's no way to fix this לולב. lulav. So from
here what so that tells you that according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda the knot that is demanded by לולב lulav is a real
full knot, okay, so שיקשור שני ראשי האגד. she-yikshor shenei rashei ha-eged.
ואוגדן כאגודה של ירק, ve-ogdan ke-agudah shel yerek,
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda if you just made it like
the vegetable thing, like just wrapping it around, לאו אגד הוא. lav
eged hu. So that's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and that's why this
לולב lulav is not fixable according to him on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Now רש״י Rashi makes an important statement. ואפילו רבנן דפליגי עליה
דרבי יהודה ואמרי לולב שאינו אגוד כשר, Ve-afillu Rabbanan de-paligi aleih de-Rabbi
Yehuda ve-ameri lulav she-eino agud kasher,
and even the Rabbis that say that if it's not knotted it's
kosher and therefore here even though you can't make a real knot
you could just you might as well just tuck it in because
even if it's not knotted it's kosher, מודו דמצוה לאוגדו. modu de-mitzvah
le-ogdo.
They would still agree that it's a מצוה mitzvah to make a
full knot, כדקתני לעיל משום זה אלי ואנוהו, ke-de-tani le-eil mishum zeh
eli ve-anvehu, וקיימא לן כרבנן. ve-kayma lan ke-Rabbanan. So what רש״י Rashi
is really saying, and this is the point I told you yesterday,
when the גמרא Gemara says the Rabbis agree because of זה אלי
ואנוהו, zeh eli ve-anvehu, are they making a purely aesthetic point or
are they saying that לכתחילה lechatchila you should do what רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda demands? And what difference does it make? Because from this
גמרא Gemara we see that what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda demands by
an אגד eged is not just the reality of physically them being
held together but a full halachically defined knot like a double knot.
And רש״י Rashi here is claiming, so if that's what you get
by רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and therefore according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda you couldn't fix this thing on יום טוב, Yom Tov, even
the Rabbis that say בדיעבד bedieved it's okay, if you want to
do the לכתחילה lechatchila for the Rabbis you need to make a
full halachic knot, you need to make a double knot. And that's
why there's a real question about those things that everybody uses, you
know those like accordion boxes type of thing, because that isn't a
double knot. I mean it holds it all tight but it isn't
a double knot. So halachically, right, if you put are you is
that the לכתחילה lechatchila the Rabbis? Would that work according to רבי
יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? And if it wouldn't work according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda then at least according to רש״י Rashi who says the
Rabbis לכתחילה lechatchila don't just want it to look pretty and to
be technically held together, they want it to be a real knot,
does is that enough? So a lot obviously the fact that so
many people do it, generally the obvious option is either not like
רש״י, Rashi, you don't really need a double knot according to the
Rabbis, or they hold that if something is held together in a
permanent way, that would count even according to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, even if it would not be a double
knot, even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda might concede if it's a type
of a permanent type of being held. Personally,
I wanting to going back decades now when I first learned this
decided okay but why it's not so clear that that's the case.
Let's really make a real double knot. And anyway I have to
tell you personally whenever I use those things it always like tears
off the leaves when you try to pull things in it. So
I just get rid of those whole accordion things and I just,
I think I've told people before, take a לולב lulav leaf, I
peel a leaf off of the לולב, lulav, split it in half,
you know because it's doubled over, then you've got the one thing,
then make like strips and you take those strips, those are really
like good tensile strength, you know they function as, and they knot
very very easily, and I just make, you know, three places on
the לולב, lulav, middle, you know, whatever, to I mean first I
do the לולב lulav itself I knot it, but then the הדסים
hadassim and ערבות aravos and I do it with these things and
I do double knots. It holds fine. I think it actually even
aesthetically I gotta tell you looks a lot nicer, looks a lot
more natural. You know you just have the whole thing like there
as one big bundle. Anyway and then it turned out... First I
do the לולב Lulav itself, I knot it, but then the הדסים
Hadassim and the ערבות Aravos and I do it with these things
and I do double knots. It holds fine. I think it actually
even aesthetically, I got to tell you, it looks a lot nicer,
looks a lot more
natural. You just have the whole thing like there is one big
bundle. Anyway and then it turned out, I just did this on
my own, then it turned out I married a woman who actually
has some לובביץ׳ Lubavitch background and turns out that this is actually
מנהג חב״ד Minhag Chabad as well. So it was all, it was
all באשערט Basherit I guess at the wedding and everything. Yeah, right.
So, two questions.
First of all, you, you used two terms. You said a bowknot
and a double knot. So the נפקא מינא Nafka Mina is a
bowknot.
No, it's a bowknot. But the גמרא Gemara says that the גמרא
Gemara says that a bowknot, you know the גמרא Gemara questioning about
the bowknot is are you allowed to make a bowknot on יום
טוב? Yom Tov? רש״י'ס Rashi's point is, the way רש״י Rashi didn't
spell out literally double knot, but what רש״י Rashi basically, his point
is that what you see from the גמרא Gemara is that it
has to count as a real knot and in the, real knot
presumably means a real knot that's a knot that would count as
a knot for the הלכה Halacha of שבת Shabbos and יום טוב,
Yom Tov, because the גמרא Gemara assumes that according to רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda there's no way you could make a knot on שבת
Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov that would work for the לולב,
Lulav, which means that any knot that works for the לולב Lulav
would be defined as a knot from שבת Shabbos and יום טוב
Yom Tov perspective. So since להלכה, Lehalacha, a knot for שבת Shabbos
and יום טוב Yom Tov is a double knot, not a bow,
well according to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda not, right, רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda might say yes, but yes, but as a general rule the
way we פסקן Pasken a knot for שבת Shabbos and יום טוב
Yom Tov is a double knot, so that might be the knot
that would be required, right.
And so does that also mean that when you bundle everything together
that you don't use like those
like slipknot things?
Right, so that would be the same question, those slipknot things. So
those slipknot things are we just tend to put on the actual
לולב Lulav itself, not to combine the לולב Lulav with the other
מינים. Minim. So there there's no הלכה Halacha of אגד. Egged. The
הלכה Halacha of אגד Egged is the לולב Lulav with the other
מינים. Minim. So I will use those, but I have to tell
you once I got in the got in the practice of doing
this thing of just using it like string it was a lot
easier to just do that for everything and
bundle first of all they have like a
million and then you pull it and it ties it together.
So hopefully we'll get to that today if we can catch up,
yeah.
How do you keep these things moist then? Because what I was
wondering also is how does that correspond to actually replacing
the הדסים Hadassim and ערבות? Aravos? Right. Right.
Well that's a good point, the fact that you could just slip
it out shows that they're not really held in any serious way
to it. Right. Right. So in theory, you know I could do
that too because you know you could slip it out and then
slip it in because it's whatever. But but then there's the question
right? Because then do you start worrying about things like like the
earlier גמרא, Gemara, like תעשה ולא מן העשוי Ta'aseh V'lo Min He'asuy
etc. Now all of that would only be within רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, but then the question is how much do you have to
worry about that within the לכתחילה Lechatchila of the רבנן? Rabbanan? So
what I basically do is the theory of what I started what
I figured out to do and it works to me totally fine
is I take a nice like kitchen towel, like a hand towel,
I get it nice and wet, you know, I wrap it all
in like I wrap it all around and then I take like
some heavy duty tin foil and I put it around that and
it holds like really tight and it keeps all the moisture in
and then I put that in like you know then put the
whole לולב Lulav in the לולב Lulav holder and it totally stays
totally moist.
You take the לולב Lulav out?
No, no, with the לולב Lulav I put but I don't wrap
the whole לולב, Lulav, I wrap the section that has the הדסים
Hadassim and ערבות Aravos with a moist you know a seriously moist
towel, I mean not so moist that I'm going to like squeeze
it and it's going to drip at the touch, but anyway and
then
I
put very heavy duty tin foil around it
and it stays totally fine and holds the moisture. And that is
so you don't even have to keep it in water? Well no,
I mean it's no and you
don't even have a refrigerator?
No, I don't do it with the refrigerator.
Do you talk about the ערבות Aravos don't get black? Yeah, I
wonder that I always had that problem. I don't know it hasn't
happened to me. If they do get black they get black whenever
everybody else's ערבות Aravos get black like towards
the middle of חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Okay, I have to replace
mine. Let's take a look. ערבה גזולה ויבשה פסולה. Arava Gezula Viyavesha
Psula. An ערבה Arava now a same משנה Mishnah that we had
by לולב Lulav and הדס Hadas now we have by the ערבה.
Arava. An ערבה Arava that is stolen or dried out is invalid.
של אשרה ושל עיר הנדחת פסולה. Shel Ashera Veshel Ir Hanidachas Psula.
Again of an אשרה Ashera worshiped or an עיר הנדחת Ir Hanidachas
which will have to be destroyed and burned is invalid. נקטם ראשו
נפרצו עליו. Niktam Rosho Nifretzu Alav. If its head is cut off
or its leaves have fallen off. צפצפה Tzaftzafa now something new. A
צפצפה Tzaftzafa which is a certain type of an ערבה Arava which
we will find out has a different types of leaves and it's
a מין Min of an a type of an ערבה Arava that's
not kosher is פסולה. Psula.
כמושה Kmusha if the leaves are wilted ושנשרו מקצת עליו Veshenishru Miktzas
Alav or only some of the leaves have fallen off ושל בעל
Veshel Ba'al and a
one from the field that is a sort of grows by rain
by rainfall okay כשרה Kshera is kosher. של בעל Shel Ba'al is
contrasted often with irrigated but here it's also contrasted to the idea
of ערבי נחל. Arvei Nachal. נחל Nachal meaning growing by a river
let's say it doesn't grow by a river it grows in a
field and has to sort of live off of the rainfall that
also is כשר. Kasher. By the way a very interesting רש״י Rashi
if you look at רש״י Rashi on the משנה. Mishnah. ערבה גזולה
ויבשה פסולה, arva gezula ve-yavesha pesula, רש"י Rashi says לולב דלכם אכולהו
קאי. lulav d'lachem akula hu kai. When it says ולקחתם לכם, u-lekachtem
lachem, it's not just referring to the לולב lulav and the אתרוג
etrog but also to the הדס hadas and the ערבה. arava. The
reason that's interesting is, number one, he could have said it by
the הדס, hadas, I don't know why he waited to say it
by the ערבה. arava. And number two, because the first discussion in
the פרק perek was whether the גזולה gezula problem is a problem
of ownership, or is the גזולה gezula problem a problem of מצוה
הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah. Here רש"י Rashi is dropping the מצוה
הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah and just focusing on the ownership aspect.
Okay, let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן,
Tanu rabanan, ערבי נחל, arvei nachal, willows of the river or of
the wadi. הגדלים על הנחל ha-gedalim al ha-nachal that they have to
grow by the wadi, okay, which is not exactly the technical requirement
even if they don't grow by a river, but at least לכתחילה
lechatchilah they should. Okay, דבר אחר, davar acher, ערבי נחל שעלה שלהן
משוך כנחל. arvei nachal she-aleh shelahen mashukh k'nachal. The leaf is elongated
like a river.
And that's going to be important because the צפצפה tzaftzafa is a
type of an ערבה arava that's invalid, which has more circular leaves.
תניא אידך, Tanya idakh, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, ערבי נחל,
arvei nachal, אין לי אלא ערבי נחל, ein li ela arvei nachal,
I only know ערבות aravos of the river. שבעל, she-baal, those that
grow in the field that survive by rainfall, ושבהרים ve-shebe-harim and that
grows on the mountains, מניין, minayin, where do I know it from?
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, ערבי נחל מכל מקום. arvei nachal mikol makom.
The ערבי arvei in לשון רבים lashon rabim means even not the
paradigmatic ערבי נחל arvei nachal but anything of that species, even if
it does not grow by the river. The רש"ש Rashash makes a
very lovely point. He says the word נחל nachal has two meanings.
It means a wadi and it means a river. So he says
that's why we're contrasting it to two cases. One is growing in
the field, which is not by a river, and the other is
growing on a mountain, which is not in a wadi. So it
doesn't need to be ערבי נחל arvei nachal either way. It doesn't
have to be a wadi and it doesn't have to be by
a river. Either way, it's okay if it's the same מין, min,
if it's the same type of plant wherever it grows.
Is there a preference since the
תורה Torah says ערבי נחל? arvei nachal? Some say, there's a discussion,
is there a לכתחילה lechatchilah of ערבי נחל? arvei nachal? רש"י Rashi
says there is. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, ערבי נחל, arvei
nachal, the first רש"י Rashi on the גמרא, Gemara, מצוה בזו. mitzvah
be-zo. Okay, that's what רש"י Rashi means, like there's a לכתחילה. lechatchilah.
There's some debate if there's a לכתחילה lechatchilah to get them that
grow by the river. אבא שאול אומר Abba Shaul omer top of
ל"ד עמוד א', lamed dalet amud aleph, אבא שאול Abba Shaul says,
ערבי שתים. arvei shtayim. ערבי arvei is לשון רבים, lashon rabim, two.
אחת ללולב ואחת למקדש achas l'lulav ve-achas l'mikdash to tell you that
there's an ערבה arava
for the לולב lulav and there's another type of an ערבה arava
that you need when they would
have hold on, talk about that in a minute, but the double
language is to tell you there are two separate מצוות mitzvos of
ערבה. arava. There's the מצוה mitzvah of ערבה arava that you do
in the לולב, lulav, that we obviously know, and then there's another
מצוה mitzvah of ערבה arava that you do separate from the לולב,
lulav, which is the one they did in the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, the walking around the altar, which we'll hear about later. So
that's what the double language says for him. רבנן, Rabanan, the רבנן
Rabbis would say, למקדש מנה להו, l'mikdash minalehun, where did they get
the idea that there's this separate מצוה mitzvah that they did in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash of walking around the altar with an
ערבה? arava? הלכתא גמירי לה. Hilkheta g'miri lah. All right, they don't
get it from a פסוק, pasuk, that's just a tradition, a הלכה
למשה מסיני. Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. דאמר
רבי אמי אמר רבי יוחנן, D'amar Rabbi Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan, עשרה
נטיעות, asara netiyot, the ten plantings, ערבה וניסוך המים, arava u-nisukh hamayim,
the ערבה arava that they would do in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash walking around the altar, and the pouring of water, הלכה למשה
מסיני. Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. Those are all הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha le-Moshe
mi-Sinai. Now, the last two are easy. The ערבה arava we know,
like what we do sort of like with הושענות, Hoshanas, we do
it with the לולב, lulav, but anyway they did it in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash with the ערבה. arava. We'll find out more
about that, the walking
around the altar. ניסוך המים nisukh hamayim is the special thing, that's
why we have שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis HaShoevah on סוכות, Sukkos,
a special pouring of water that they did with the morning sacrifice
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash over סוכות, Sukkos, the only time
they would ever pour water on the altar. The עשרה נטיעות asara
netiyot is an unrelated point. It is the idea that on a
שמיטה Shmita year you stop working the land already ערב שמיטה, erev
Shmita, already the period before שמיטה. Shmita. Some types of things you
stop working
from פסח, Pesach, like six months before the שמיטה Shmita year begins,
some areas you stop working from
שבועות, Shavuos, whatever four months or so before פסח Pesach begins. But
if you have trees, you can work the area underneath the trees
like right
up to like within a month before the שמיטה Shmita year begins.
Now, let's say you actually have, hold on, let me just check
רש"י Rashi for a second, see what רש"י Rashi says
one minute
right, so here's basically the הלכה. halakha. If you have old trees,
you can work the area directly under these old trees, which sort
of need a lot of nutrient and irrigation, until a month before
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. But if you have young trees, you can
actually work them right up
to If you have ten trees in a field that is fifty
by fifty אמות, amot, and they're dispersed equally within that field, you're
allowed to work not just directly under the trees, but you're allowed
to irrigate and work the entire field for the sake of those
young trees all the way up to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah itself.
You don't have to add anything onto שמיטה Shemittah in that type
of a—in that scenario. So that's the special הלכה halacha of ten
young trees. Ten young trees dispersed equally in a field of fifty
by fifty אמות, amot, you can work the whole field. Whereas if
it was not ten, or if they weren't dispersed equally, or the
field was larger, these types of things, you could only work under
the trees; you couldn't work the entire field. Okay, so we're not
going to worry about that. The only interesting thing to point out
is why are these three bunched together? There's a lot of things
that are הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. So רש"י Rashi says,
well, these happen to all be discussed at the same time in
the בית מדרש, beit midrash, so that's why they were bunched together.
But probably they're also bunched together because—not probably, but they all do
relate to water. Right, exactly. So presumably the water connection is what
brings them all together. The same—so anyway, and so—but that's the basic
point. We know the idea of ערבה aravah from הלכה למשה מסיני;
halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai; we don't know it from the verse. Now by
the way, תוספות Tosafot asks an interesting
question. תוספות Tosafot says—let's take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot
says like this: ורבנן למקדש מנלן, v'rabbanan l'mikdash minalan, תוספות Tosafot on
ל"ד ע"א. lamed-daled amud-aleph. He says, הכא נמי מטי למיבעי לאבא שאול
ערבה של הרים מנא ליה. hacha nami mati l'mibaye l'Abba Shaul aravah
shel harim minalei. He says, so אבא שאול Abba Shaul who learns
that the, you know, ערבה aravah is one for the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, where does he know the idea that you can use
them even if they don't grow by a river? So he says,
ושמא לית ליה, v'shema leit lei, maybe he holds that if they
don't grow by a river, it's invalid because he needs the word
ערבי arvei to tell you the one that's used for the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And then he says, ולפי
זה, v'lefi zeh, says תוספות Tosafot about six lines down, צריך ליזהר
שלא ליטול ערבה ללולב אלא אם כן גדלה על הנחל. tzarich lizaher
shelo litol aravah l'lulav ela im kein gedilah al hanachal.
Maybe we should say that you can only use an ערבה, aravah,
not like the גמרא Gemara says, only if it really grows by
a river. Why? דשתי דרשות לא דרשינן מערבי כדדרשינן לקמן. de-shtei derashot
lo darshinan m'arvei k'didarshinan l'kaman.
Because later we're going to say the double language of ערבי arvei
is going to tell you two, because how many ערבות aravot do
you have on a לולב? lulav? Two. So if later we say
the double language of ערבי arvei says you need two ערבות, aravot,
maybe we can't use—we can't include the other type of an ערבה
aravah that doesn't grow literally by a river. So תוספות Tosafot has
the possibility that you would need to have ערבות aravot that grow
by a river to be יוצא. yotzei. If we're—if we're—right, not because
of אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, but if we're going to later say
the double language is to demand two ערבות, aravot, so maybe it's
not coming to include those that don't grow by river. We don't
פוסק pasquen that way; that would be a really nice big חומרא,
chumra, but—but that is a possibility because of the דרשה, derashah, the
way the גמרא Gemara learns it out. Okay, back to the גמרא.
Gemara. No, תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. ערבי נחל הגדלות על הנחל. arvei
nachal hagedilot al hanachal.
So meaning those that grow by the river. Now we just got
through saying it doesn't have to be, even תוספות, Tosafot, literally grow
by a river, but at least it's the species that grows by
the river. So פרט לצפצפה הגדלה בין ההרים, prat l'tzaftzafah hagedilah bein
heharim,
to exclude the צפצפה tzaftzafah species that generally grows in the mountains.
Now of course we just said a minute ago you can use
an ערבה aravah that grows in the mountains. Fine, but it's the
species that is the classic species that grows by the river, as
opposed to a צפצפה, tzaftzafah, which is a different species that fundamentally
grows in the mountains. So it's not a question of practically where
this thing grew, but what type of a species it is. Correct,
it doesn't matter where it grows. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira,
מאי קרא, mai kra, where do you see a verse that צפצפה
tzaftzafah is considered a—a like a low—you know, a less
quality—a type of an ערבה aravah and therefore should be like a
downgraded type of an ערבה? aravah? קח על מים רבים צפצפה שמו,
kach al mayim rabbim tzaftzafah samo, take on many
waters, you have made it into a צפצפה. tzaftzafah. So this is
a verse that is like in the context of a curse of
the Jewish people and it says the way it's going to be
read, which the גמרא Gemara will say in a minute, it used
to be a type of a plant that would be on all
these waters and now it has become a צפצפה. tzaftzafah. So you
see a צפצפה tzaftzafah is a lesser plant that does not generally
grow by the waters. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, ודילמא
פירושי קמפרש, v'dilma perushei kamfaresh,
how do you know that it's sort of downgrading it? Maybe it's
just explaining it. מאי קח
על מים רבים, mai kach al mayim rabbim, take that thing that
grows by many waters, ומנו, u-manhu, what is that? צפצפה. tzaftzafah. So
maybe צפצפה tzaftzafah is a type of a thing that grows by
many waters; maybe it's not a lesser type of a plant. So
it says, אם כן מאי שמו, im kein mai samo, if so,
what does it mean it has made them into a צפצפה tzaftzafah
or made it into a צפצפה? tzaftzafah? That means it used to
be a better type of a plant that grew by water; it
has now become a צפצפה. tzaftzafah. So you see that a צפצפה
tzaftzafah is a lesser and it's not the type of species that
generally grows by water, and therefore it is not considered good for
an ערבה aravah wherever it grows. אמר רבי אבהו אמר הקדוש ברוך
הוא, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, and now we're going
to explain the—the metaphor of the verse. אני אמרתי שיהיו ישראל לפני
כקח על מים רבים. Ani amarti she-yihyu Yisrael lefanai k'kach al mayim
rabbim.
I said the Jewish people should be before me like one who
takes on many
waters. it's taken for the
מצווה. mitzvah. והן שמו עצמן, V'hein samu atzman,
they פסלו passelled themselves, they made themselves like the צפצפה tziphtzafa that
grows in the mountains and they made themselves something that could not
be taken for the מצווה, mitzvah, they sort of pushed themselves out
of this holy context. איכא דמתני לה להאי קרא אמתניתא. Ika d'matni
la le'hai kra a'matnisa.
Now some say where this is just going to be a repeat,
but rather than sort of having it as רבי
זירא Rebbi Zeira quoting the verse to explain why a צפצפה tziphtzafa
is no good, that the verse was already embedded in the ברייתא.
braisa. כקח מים רבים צפצפה שמו, K'kach mayim rabim tziphtzafa samu, that
the ברייתא braisa itself said that you can't use a צפצפה tziphtzafa
and it quoted the verse. מתקיף לה רבי זירא. Maskif la Rebbi
Zeira. Now רבי זירא, Rebbi Zeira, rather than quoting the verse, asked
on the verse. דילמא פירושי קמפרש, Dilma perushei k'mefaresh, כקח מים רבים
ומאי ניהו צפצפה? k'kach mayim rabim u'mai nihu tziphtzafa? Maybe צפצפה tziphtzafa
is the is the name of that thing that grows on many
waters? Maybe it's not a lesser type of a plant? No. אם
כן מאי שמו? Im kein mai samu? Then what would שמו samu
mean? שמו Samu means it's being downgraded. אמר רבי אבהו אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא אני אמרתי שיהיו ישראל לפני כקח מים רבים ומאי ניהו
ערבה והן שמו עצמן כצפצפה שבהרים. Amar Rebbi Abahu Amar HaKadosh Baruch
Hu Ani amarti she'yehyu Yisrael lefanai k'kach mayim rabim u'mai nihu arava
v'hein samu atzman k'tziphtzafa she'be'harim. It says basically a complete repeat except
it starts with having that verse in the ברייתא braisa rather than
having רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira to be the one to quote the
verse. So now we have said that because of that verse we
see that צפצפה tziphtzafa is not the קח, kach, is not the
thing that is taken for the לולב, lulav, is not the thing
that's על מים רבים, al mayim rabim, it's fundamentally a different species.
And therefore the actual ערבה arava doesn't have to grow by the
river, the צפצפה tziphtzafa no matter where it grows is a different
lesser species and is no good. And that's our פסק psak that
of course an ערבה arava is good even if it does not
grow by the river, except according to תוספות Tosafos that wants to
make it an issue because if we use the פסוק pasuk to
tell us that you need two ערבות, aravos, תוספות Tosafos wants to
sort of resurface that as a problem, but the general assumption is
it doesn't have to grow by a river. Now that now that
we've said that's the difference, how do you identify the difference between
a צפצפה tziphtzafa and an ערבה? arava? Let's take a look. תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: איזו ערבה ואיזו צפצפה? Eizu arava v'eizu tziphtzafa?
So what's an ערבה, arava, what's a צפצפה? tziphtzafa? ערבה: Arava: קנה
שלה אדום, kanah shelah adom,
it has a red twig, and if you look actually at the
ערבות, aravos, you know some, you know some of them actually, not
all of them, we'll talk about in a minute, well it might
be that it starts red and then it turns color, but anyway
it has a red twig. ועלה שלה משוך, v'alah shelah mashoch,
and the leaf is elongated, as we mentioned before, that's also part
of the suggestion of the word ערבה, arava, נחל. nachal. ופיה חלק,
u'piah chalak, and the edges of the leaf are smooth. צפצפה, Tziphtzafa,
the צפצפה's tziphtzafa different in all three ways. קנה שלה לבן, kanah
shelah lavan, it has a white stick, ועלה שלה עגול, v'alah shelah
agol,
and it's a circular leaf, ופיה דומה למגל, u'piah domeh l'magal,
and the edges of the leaf is like a scythe,
it's serrated. So that's and that's and of course it said three
qualities that make it an ערבה arava and the three opposite qualities
make it a צפצפה. tziphtzafa. What if it has only some of
the qualities of the ערבה, arava, right? So if you take a
look תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos has
interprets this very leniently. תוספות Tosafos says קנה שלה, kanah shelah, תוספות
Tosafos says כיון
דפירש ג' סימני ערבה, kivan d'peireish g' simanei arava, if once it
said the three characters of an ערבה, arava, הוי סגי, havi sagi,
it could have ended there, these are the three characters of an
ערבה, arava, anything that doesn't have these three is invalid. אלא להכשיר
אף שאין בו ג' סימנים אלו. Ella l'hachshir af she'ein bo g'
simanim elu.
The reason it says the three opposite qualities are in the צפצפה
tziphtzafa is to tell you you don't need all three to be
an ערבה. arava. חילופא גילא לפיכך תני סימני צפצפה למימר דוקא הני.
Chilufa gila l'phi-kach tani simanei tziphtzafa l'meimar davka hani. Only if it
has the three bad qualities is it not good. Okay? That if
it has so you don't need all three good qualities to be
good. So it's quite interesting, right? The גמרא Gemara often does that,
it describes both extremes and leaves you wondering what's the story in
the case in the middle. So תוספות Tosafos actually interprets it very
leniently. It's only a problem if it has all three negative qualities.
Okay? Again, interesting question because sometimes you will get an ערבה, arava,
A, that doesn't have a red stick, although sometimes it might have
been red but it just turns color, but B, you know you
will get an ערבה arava that sometimes the leaf, as you know,
there's some ערבות aravos that are much longer leaves and there's some
that are more roundish leaves, also difference in הדסים, hadassim, some are
longer and some are much rounder. Okay, so which which
of you need all these qualities or some of them? Again, not
clear. תוספות Tosafos basically comes out very leniently that you only need
some of them. I'm not פוסק'ן paskening here. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. The גמרא Gemara says והתניא. v'atanya. So now
we said if it has a what do you call it, if
it's got a scythe-like leaf it's no, the edges are no good.
So the גמרא Gemara says
והתניא v'atanya דומה למגל כשר. domeh l'magal kasher. One minute, we have
a ברייתא braisa that says that even if the leaf is like
a scythe it's kosher, even with the serrated. דומה למסר פסול. domeh
l'masar pasul. If it's like a knife or like a saw it's
invalid. What's the difference? The difference is that a scythe all of
the serrations go in one direction, like they're angled
things.
That's one type of thing, so it cuts in either way you
move, right? That's, you know, as opposed to serrations that go like
this, right? Where it only cuts if you're moving in one direction
as opposed to in the other direction. Okay, so that's so if
it's like if it's if it's got if it's got edges on
both sides, if it's more triangular like a saw, it's no good,
whereas if it's like a scythe and it's only serrated in one
direction...
Oh, you mean a double edge, meaning on one end and the
other? Like, you know, meaning of your knife? Yeah, you know, with
the points, you can have it on both sides, you know what
I'm saying?
On the blade? Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. That's not what we're talking
about. It's not talking about both, it's talking about, yeah, talking, yeah.
Okay, so anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. So, so which
is it? If it's done if it's like a מגל, magal, is
it כשר kosher or פסול? pasul? So גמרא Gemara says, אמר אביי
כי תניא היא בחילפא גילא. Amar Abaye, ki tanya hi be-chilfa gila.
That thing that is when it's like a מגל magal it's כשר,
kosher, it's a different type of a species called a חילפא גילא.
chilfa gila. Okay, which is a
so if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, he says like
this, three lines down in the wide lines, חילפא גילא מין ערבה
כשירה היא ופיה דומה למגל אבל שאר ערבה פיה חלק. Chilfa gila
min arava kesheira hi u-piha domeh le-magal aval shear arava piha halak.
So רש"י Rashi basically says, and this is reinforcing or this is
based where תוספות Tosafot gets this point from, there are some species
of ערבה arava that do have leaves that are serrated that are
כשר, kosher, right?
So there are species, so meaning not all species when we said
if it's serrated like a scythe it's invalid, that's not a universally
true. There are some species that serrated like a knife, like a
saw is invalid, and there's some species like this חילפא גילא chilfa
gila that it's serrated like a scythe that it is valid. Okay,
now how do you know which is which? You have to know
your species of ערבה, arava, okay? But that is, but that's basically
תוספות's Tosafot point, the way תוספות Tosafot seems to want to read
it is, is that it only if it has all three problems
is it invalid. So presumably חילפא גילא, chilfa gila, while it might
be serrated like a scythe, the other qualities it has are the
classic ערבה arava qualities and therefore it is good. Okay, so that's
the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara. Is this type of a serration
bad or good? Sometimes it's a bad species, sometimes it's a good
species, there's a species called חילפא גילא chilfa gila which actually is
okay. How do you know is not very clear, according to תוספות
Tosafot the answer might be, as I said, because some of the
other characteristics it has are the good characters. Yes, Mike?
So when we said,
I want to understand one thing about a שדה בעל, Sedeh Baal,
or something that doesn't need to be irrigated, but if it so
it means if you have a field that you do irrigate, you
know, and needs to be irrigated, you couldn't use anything that grew
there for הושענא, Hoshanah, right?
No. בעל Baal is in contrast to growing by the river. Okay,
it doesn't matter whether it's whether it's rainwater or irrigated or river,
it's just contrasting with something that grows by the river. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says
אביי, Abaye, who just got through saying that חילפא גילא, chilfa gila,
שמע מינה האי חילפא גילא כשירה להושענא, shema mina hai chilfa gila
kashra le-hoshana, since we have to identify a certain type of an
ערבה arava that has a serrations that's good, so and I've to
identify this חילפא גילא, chilfa gila, then we can infer that חילפא
גילא chilfa gila is good for the ערבה. arava. So the גמרא
Gemara says, by the way, quite interesting here, because here it uses
the word הושענא hoshana to refer to the ערבה arava and if
you remember before it used the word הושענא hoshana to refer to
the הדסים, hadassim, which are cut for this, right? So the גמרא
Gemara says, you know, actually it was a similar statement, right? It
says it said before when you cut the הדסים hadassim it says,
right? It was that was גמרא Gemara way back on ל"ד, lamed
amud dalet, it says where was it? זיבניתו אסא zavenitu asa and
then it says השתא הושענא מי קייט. hashtah hoshana mei kait. Here
it's called a הושענא, hoshana, and yesterday as well it spoke about
when אביי Abaye said you can you hear that the type of
thing that's כשר kosher for a לולב, lulav, he said it was
the same אביי, Abaye, שמע מינה האי אסא מצראה כשירה להושענא. shema
mina hai asa mitzra kashra le-hoshana. So הושענא hoshana seems to be
the word for anything that's part of the bundle together with the
לולב, lulav, not just the הדס, hadas, not just the ערבה, arava,
but the bundling together with the לולב lulav is called the הושענא.
hoshana. So this so this ערבה arava is כשר, kosher, this חילפא
גילא chilfa gila is the species that's כשר kosher to use for
the לולב. lulav. פשיטא, peshita, obviously? No, מהו דתימא, mahu de-teima, I
might have thought, הואיל ואית ליה שם לוואי, ho-il ve-it lei shem
livai, same point as before, since it's got some type of a
of a
descriptive name associated with it, it's not just straight ערבה, arava, it's
the חילפא גילא chilfa gila ערבה, arava, so שם לוואי לא נכשר
shem livai lo nifkesher won't be כשר, kosher, קא משמע לן kamashma
lan that it is. ואימא הכי נמי, ve-eima hachi nami, now maybe
we should say that? No, ערבי נחל אמר רחמנא מכל מקום, arvei
nahal amar rachmana mi-kol makom, ערבי נחל arvei nahal is not again
classic only ערבה, arava, ערבי arvei in the plural means anything that's
one of the subspecies of ערבה. arava. Again, not a צפצפה, tzaftzafa,
that's seen as again completely unrelated because it's not like of the
type that normally grows by a נחל, nahal, that identifies it as
fundamentally out of the ערבי נחל arvei nahal category. But if it's
within the ערבי נחל, arvei nahal, even if it's not the paradigmatic
species, any one of the subspecies of ערבי נחל. arvei nahal. is
sufficient. Okay. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, said רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda, הני תלת מילי אשתנו שמייהו מדחרב בית המקדש. hani telat milei
ishtanu shemayehu mi-de-charav Beis HaMikdash. The following three three things, the names
were reversed from the time the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed.
חילפתא ערבתא ערבתא חילפתא. chilfasa aravsa, aravsa chilfasa. The things that we
used to call ערבה, aravah, we now call חילפתא. chilfasa. It's not
חילפא גילא, chilfa gila, which is actually kosher, but חילפתא chilfasa used
to be the name of invalid ערבות, aravos, like the צפצפה. tzaftzafa.
And now, but so and and ערבות aravos were the names of
kosher things that we now call חילפתא chilfasa used to be called
ערבתא aravsa and vice versa. So if you wanted to know what's
a kosher ערבה aravah nowadays, you should go around and ask, what
are things that we're calling חילפתא? chilfasas? Because we're now calling חילפתא
chilfasas things that used to be called ערבתא aravsa and vice versa.
מאי נפקא מינה? Mai nafka mina? ללולב. Le-lulav. For the לולב, lulav,
that if you want to identify the kosher species of ערבה aravah
now, those are things that go by the name
חילפתא. chilfasa.
Okay. שיפורא חצוצרתא חצוצרתא שיפורא. shipura chatzotzarta, chatzotzarta shipura. שופר Shofar is
now called a חצוצרת, chatzotzeret, which is a trumpet, and things that
used to be called a trumpet are now called the שופר. shofar.
So מאי נפקא מינה? mai nafka mina? לשופר של ראש השנה. Le-shofar
shel Rosh HaShanah. So you should know that if you're looking for
a שופר shofar for ראש השנה, Rosh HaShanah, don't go around saying,
I'd like a שופר, shofar, they'll give you a trumpet. You need
to go around saying, I want a חצוצרת chatzotzeret and then you'll
get a שופר. shofar. Now, by the way, רש"י Rashi says, what,
I mean, what is the trumpet? Normally, we that would imply like
a man-made metal object. So then, like, do I really need them
to tell me don't use that for a שופר? shofar? But okay,
רש"י Rashi says that no, the difference is is that a חצוצרת
chatzotzeret suggests one that's like a simple straight one as opposed to
a שופר shofar suggests a more like bent type of a thing.
And therefore, you're not you're supposed to use a bent שופר shofar
for ראש השנה Rosh HaShanah and not one that's just, you know,
straight. By the way, interestingly, the שאילתות, She'iltos, which is a Gaonic
work in the מצוה mitzvah to blow the שופר shofar on ראש
השנה, Rosh HaShanah, says דמחייבי דבית ישראל למתקע בחצוצרתא. de-mechayvei de-veis Yisrael
le-mitka be-chatzotzarta. Okay, that we're obligated to blow a חצוצרתא. chatzotzarta. Because
this is reflecting the fact that the language had shifted and the
word חצוצרת chatzotzeret meant שופר. shofar.
Well, no, רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi's point is that what what what
did חצוצרת chatzotzeret used to mean or what does שופר shofar now
mean? Does it now mean a phys like a metal trumpet or
does it mean no, an animal thing that's straight as opposed to
twisted? Okay, but the גמרא Gemara does indicate that the words had
reversed. Okay. Now, פתורתא פתורא פתורא פתורתא. patorta patora, patora patorta. These
are two different words for different types of like tables and one
was big and one was small and which was which, the names
changed. למאי נפקא מינה? Le-mai nafka mina? What difference does it make
to know which what's called what? למקח וממכר. Le-mekach u-memkar. That if
you agree to sell or buy a table, you gotta know which
type of table you're talking about. Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי
Abaye said, אף אני אומר, af ani omer, what now they're talking
about things that names reversed, I'll add to the list. בית כסי
הובלילא הובלילא בית כסי. beis kasei hovleila, hovleila beis kasei. So these
are different types of inner organs in the in an animal, a
בית הכוסות beis ha-kosos and הובלילא, hovleila, I don't know how they
translated it, whatever, it's a part of the stomach. Wonderful. למאי נפקא
מינה? Le-mai nafka mina? למחט הנמצאת בעובי בית הכוסות. le-machat ha-nimtzes be-ovi
beis ha-kosos. If you have a needle inside the walls of one
of these organs, so there's a difference between which organ it is
and you have to know which of the organs we're talking about.
רש"י Rashi says one's the first chamber and
another is the omasum. Fine, it's in it's fine, but I am
not going to unpack that now. We'll have enough we'll worry about
that enough when we get to חולין. Chullin. אמר רבא בר יוסף,
Amar Rava bar Yosef, אף אני אומר, af ani omer, I'll add
to this list. בבל בורסיף בורסיף בבל. Bavel Borsif, Borsif Bavel. What
used to be called בבל Bavel is now called בורסיף Borsif and
what used to be called בורסיף Borsif is now called בבל. Bavel.
למאי נפקא מינה? Le-mai nafka mina? What difference does it make? לגיטי
נשים. le-gitei nashim. For גט, get, now what does that mean? So
you could mean, you would think it means, oh, when you've have
to write somebody where somebody comes from and they come from בבל,
Bavel, so don't get it confused, know that what used to be
called בבל Bavel is now בורסיף. Borsif. But תוספות Tosafot says, so
רש"י Rashi says, תוספות Tosafot says that can't be what it means
because we don't put countries in the גט, get, we only put
cities and בבל Bavel is a country. So תוספות Tosafot and רש"י
Rashi both say the נפקא מינה nafka mina is for the first
משנה Mishnah in גיטין Gittin where it says that when you come
from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you don't have to say בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם. bifnai nichtav u-vifnai nechtam. When you come from חוץ לארץ
chutz la-aretz you do, if a שליח shaliach is bringing a גט
get to testify that it was written and signed correctly. And the
גמרא Gemara says when you come from בבל Bavel you also do
not have to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. bifnai nichtav u-vifnai nechtam.
So you should know that that exclusion of בבל Bavel from that
הלכה halacha applies to the area now referred to as בורסיף, Borsif,
not the area that used to be referred to as בורסיף, Borsif,
that which is the area that used to be referred to as
בבל. Bavel. Okay, let's move on.
Also have to mention that Babylon the city was abandoned by the
time of the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. Let's take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. רבי ישמעאל אומר,
Rabi Yishmael omer, שלשה הדסים. shlosha hadassim. Now that we mentioned the
לולב, lulav, הדס, hadas, and ערבה aravah before we get to the
אתרוג, esrog, we're going to talk about the the group of the
לולב, lulav, הדס, hadas, and ערבה aravah that all get grouped together.
So let's take a look.
שלשה הדסים, Shlosha hadassim, you need three הדסים, hadassim, ושתי ערבות, u-shtei
aravos, two ערבות, aravos, ולולב אחד, ve-lulav echad, ואתרוג אחד, ve-esrog echad,
one לולב, lulav, one אתרוג, esrog, which is exactly what we do.
But then he adds an interesting line. אפילו שנים קטומים. afilu shnayim
ketumim. Of those three הדסים, hadassim, two can be have their heads
cut off, two and only one has to be perfect, which the
גמרא Gemara says like, "Make up your mind. If you need three,
they all have to be good. If you need one, if you
only need one, then why do if you have two then if
you two can have their heads cut off, either they could all
be good with their heads cut off or none of them good.
What's the split that two is okay and one not?" Okay, we'll
get look worry about that. רבי טרפון אומר אפילו שלושתם קטומים. Rabbi
Tarfon omer afilu sheloshtam ketumim. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says all three
can have their heads cut off, which is interesting because why all
of a sudden are we debating this issue of הדס hadas by
their heads cut off and not by ערבה? aravah? רש"י Rashi says
that according to רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon he doesn't need הדר, hadar,
but if you look at the last רש"י Rashi in the משנה,
Mishna, דלא בעי הדר בהדס. delo ba'ei hadar behadas. He doesn't need
הדר hadar by הדס, hadas, which is bizarre. Like, why the הדס
hadas doesn't need a הדר hadar and the לולב lulav and the
ערבה aravah do? So the whole idea that you could have a
הדס קטום hadas katum and there should be a separate הלכה halacha
by the הדס hadas by this regard of קטום, katum, you could
have said maybe the הדס hadas doesn't is- isn't doesn't become un-הדר
hadar with the head cut off, it's a bigger problem by the
לולב lulav and ערבה aravah just in terms of what aesthetic reality
is created. But to say in principle you don't need הדר, hadar,
why the הדס hadas should be excluded is bizarre. So on the
one hand you have this issue about whether you need about the
הדס, hadas, whether it can be קטום katum or not קטום. katum.
But the other issue is how many of each that you need.
רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, כשם
שלולב אחד ואתרוג אחד כך הדס אחד וערבה אחת. keshem shelulav echad
ve'esrog echad kach hadas echad ve'aravah achas. There's one לולב, lulav, one
אתרוג, esrog, one הדס, hadas, one ערבה. aravah. It sounds like it
says like, you know, one God, one Torah, one Jewish people. Now
I should say that I don't mean that only in joke because
there's a quite shocking מדרש Midrash according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
that describes the symbolism of the ארבעה מינים arba'ah minim and he
describes each of the ארבעה מינים arba'ah minim is כנגד הקדוש ברוך
הוא. keneged Hakadosh Baruch Hu. And he quotes a פסוק. pasuk. לולב
זה הקדוש ברוך הוא, lulav zeh Hakadosh Baruch Hu, you know, אתרוג
זה הקדוש ברוך הוא, esrog zeh Hakadosh Baruch Hu, הדס זה הקדוש
ברוך הוא, hadas zeh Hakadosh Baruch Hu, which really evokes this almost
very, you know, kabbalistic idea of bringing together like somehow the different
aspects of the divine, you know, and sort of seeing that as
what the whole idea of the לולב lulav is. So that is
there's actually a מדרש Midrash that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that
and therefore combining that with the idea that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says only one לולב, lulav, one הדס, hadas, one ערבה, aravah, you
know, one wonders if there's some correspondence there. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. תניא, Tanya, we learned in the ברייתא: Braisa:
רבי ישמעאל אומר פרי עץ הדר אחת כפות תמרים אחת ענף עץ
עבות שלושה ערבי נחל
שתיים.
Rabbi Yishmael omer peri etz hadar achas kapos temarim achas anaf etz
avos sheloshah arvei nachal
shetayim.
Now where's he getting it from? So if he's getting ענף עץ
עבות anaf etz avos from the fact that there's three words and
ערבי נחל arvei nachal from the fact that there's two words or
ערבי arvei is in plural, so why not learn פרי עץ הדר
peri etz hadar three אתרוגים, esrogim, כפות תמרים kapos temarim two? You
know, so it's not exactly clear but תוספות Tosafos raises the question.
Not exactly clear, obviously the last two seem to be by the
number of words or ערבי arvei by the plural, but how you're
limited to one לולב lulav and one אתרוג esrog at the is
not so clear.
How do you get more? I mean some people take more הדסים?
hadassim?
Well we'll talk about that later. But so, ערבי נחל שתיים. arvei
nachal shetayim. ואפילו שניים קטומים, ve'afilu shenayim ketumim, even if two of
the הדסים hadassim have their are cut off, or the tips are
cut off, ואחד שאינו קטום ve'echad she'eino katum and one is not.
רבי טרפון אומר Rabbi Tarfon omer שלושה sheloshah three, ואפילו שלושתם קטומים
ve'afilu sheloshtan ketumim all three can have their heads cut off. רבי
עקיבא אומר כשם שלולב אחד ואתרוג אחד כך הדס אחד וערבה אחת.
Rabbi Akiva omer keshem shelulav echad ve'esrog echad kach hadas echad ve'aravah
achas. אמרו לו רבי אליעזר, amru lo Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer said, יחי יהא אתרוג עמהם באגודה אחת? yehi yehei esrog imahem
ba'agudah achas? Now it's interesting why אמרו לו amru lo because who's
he disagreeing with? But anyway, maybe the אתרוג esrog should be bound
up together with the לולב, lulav, הדס, hadas, and ערבה aravah in
one bound bond. אמרת, amarta, וכי נאמר פרי עץ הדר וכפות תמרים?
vechi ne'emar peri etz hadar vekapos temarim? It doesn't say פרי עץ
הדר peri etz hadar and כפות תמרים. kapos temarim. והלא לא נאמר
אלא כפות. vehalo lo ne'emar ela kapos. פרי עץ הדר peri etz
hadar then there's no ו. vav. כפות תמרים וענף עץ עבות וערבי
נחל. kapos temarim ve'anaf etz avos ve'arvei nachal. So the fact that
the אתרוג esrog is not joined to the לולב lulav with a
ו vav shows that you bunch the לולב lulav with the הדס
hadas and ערבה aravah and you keep the אתרוג esrog separate. ומניין
שמעכבין זה את זה? uminayin sheme'akvin zeh es zeh? How do you
know that they prevent you from one the other, meaning if you
don't have all ארבעה מינים arba'ah minim you're not יוצא? yotzei? How
do you know that? תלמוד לומר ולקחתם, talmud lomar ulekachtem, you shall
take them. And really means you shall take for you, but שתהא
לקיחה תמה. shetehei lekichah tamah. The דרשה derasha is ולקחתם. ulekachtam.
It should be a full taking, you have to take all of
them together, you cannot just take a few and be יוצא. yotzei.
It's actually interesting because you can take them at different times. You
can pick up the לולב, lulav, then pick up the הדס, hadas,
then pick up the ערבה, aravah, then pick up the אתרוג esrog
and you're יוצא. yotzei. But what we learn from ולקחתם ulekachtem is
you're not יוצא yotzei unless you take all four of them. Okay.
Now נחזור לרבי יהודה nachzor leRabbi Yehudah who
says it needs an אגד, eged, right? Right. Okay.
רבי
ישמעאל מאי משמע? Rabbi Yishmael mai mashma? Now what's this רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael idea of two heads cut off and one not? אי
שלמים בעי, ei shelemim ba'ei, if you need them to be whole,
בני נמי כולהו, benei nami kuleihu, all should be whole. אי לא
בעי שלמים, ei lo ba'ei shelemim, if you don't need whole, אפילו
חד נמי לא, afilu chad nami lo, then even if then they
should all three be able to be cut. אמר בירא אמר רבי
אמי, amar Bira amar Rabbi Ami, חזר בו רבי ישמעאל. chazar bo
Rabbi Yishmael. All right, he reversed himself. So which one did he
reverse himself from? So רש"י Rashi says... He reversed himself from the
requirement of three. And really בדיעבד bedi'avad he winds up really saying
you know really bottom line I really only need one. And therefore
two of them can have their heads cut because I really don't
need three. Again, it's strange. It does not sound like that. Sounds
like Rabbi Ishmael feels like one is core and the other two
are sort of like necessary but not as central. But the Gemara
doesn't can understand how that all works together. אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel הלכה כרבי טרפון. halacha keRabbi Tarfon.
We rule like Rabbi Tarfon that says all three can have their
heads cut off, which is interesting. ואזדא שמואל לטעמיה, va'azda Shmuel letaymeih,
goes according to his reasoning, דאמר להו שמואל להנך דמזבני אסא, de'amar
lehu Shmuel lehanu demizabni asa,
Shmuel said to people that sell the הדסים, hadassim, אזלו וזבינו, azlu
vezabinu,
you'd better lower your prices and sell at a reasonable
price. ואי לא, ve'i lo, and if you don't, if you start
hiking up your prices, דרשינא לכו כרבי טרפון, darshina lechu keRabbi Tarfon,
I will
I will expound the position of Rabbi Tarfon, and I will say
that you can use them with their heads cut off and therefore
there goes your whole market because now people won't pay a premium
to get full הדסים. hadassim. So if people so if you want
so you'd better you'd better sell them at a reasonable price. So
the Gemara says מאי טעמא mai ta'ama now why is he threatening
to teach them Rabbi Tarfon? אילימא משום דמיקל, ileima mishum de'meikel, if
it's because Rabbi Tarfon is a lenient position, לידרוש להו כרבי עקיבא
דמיקל טפי, lidrosh lehu keRabbi Akiva de'meikel tfei,
why not say Rabbi Akiva who only demands one? So the Gemara
says: No. תלתא קטומי שכיחי tlasa kitumei shechichi
because it's actually it's much easier to get three with their heads
cut off. חד ולא קטום לא שכיח chad velo katum lo shechich
and to get one perfect is less is is harder. So actually
it would make it it would make it much easier for people
to demand three if you could allow קטום katum than to demand
just one. So if you really want to threaten them, the bigger
threat is to tell you you can use them קטומים ktumim even
three קטומים. ktumim. Now by the way, the Gemara, you know תוספות
Tosafot says what do you mean threatening this way, threatening that way?
If you פוסק paskin like Rabbi Tarfon, you're only going to threaten
them with what you פוסק paskin like, not with what you don't
פוסק paskin like. Okay?
So that's what the Gemara's sort of saying. Like the Gemara's trying
to say, I'll prove to you he holds like Rabbi Tarfon, because
if he was just threatening them and he didn't really hold like
it, he should have threatened them with Rabbi Akiva's position. And רש"י
Rashi says: No, that's not a proof, because maybe Rabbi Tarfon is
a more threatening position than Rabbi Akiva's position. But anyway, the conclusion
is that Shmuel holds like Rabbi Tarfon and again it's a fascinating
point. If we פוסק paskin that way, why is it that the
הדס hadas could be קטום katum and other things don't have to
be can't be קטומים? ktumim? Is it like רש"י Rashi says fundamentally
you don't need הדר? hadar? Why should הדס hadas have a different
fundamental demand of הדר hadar than other things? So one is the
interesting issue of קטומים, ktumim, but the other is the fascinating question
of the numbers, where you get the numbers and the idea that
Rabbi Akiva says only one of each and he doesn't agree with
this issue of numbers. Tomorrow maybe I'll talk on the issue that
Michael raised, which is what if you have more than the מנין,
minyan, is that an issue or not? That comes up in the
ראשונים, we'll touch on that tomorrow.